Finding Aid for Jean Worth Papers, ca. 1869-1986
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jean Worth Papers circa 1869-1986
Worth, Jean, 1904-1987.
8 linear feet
89137 Aa 2
Escanaba, Michigan, newspaperman. Subject files (including collected materials) relating to his research interest in Michigan's Upper Peninsula, notably in the area of Cedar River, Escanaba, and Menominee; include manuscript of writings, subject files, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Jean Worth papers were donated by his children: Ann Worth Concannon, Jean Worth Clair, and Dooley Worth. (Donor no. 4171 )
The collection is open to research.
Jean Worth was born May 5, 1904 in Menominee, Michigan. After graduating from the public schools in 1922, he joined the staff of the Menominee Herald-Leader. In 1923 he left Menominee to attend the American Academy of Dramatic Arts in New York City, and was graduated from that institution in 1925. In 1928 Worth took a position with the Detroit Times as a rewrite man and assistant in editorial promotion. He left Detroit to rejoin the staff of the Herald-Leader in 1930 as city editor. He was promoted to managing editor in 1934, and to editor in 1943. He served in this capacity until 1955, when he assumed editorship of the Escanaba Daily Press. He held this position until his retirement in 1969. During his retirement Worth served as a consultant to Upper Peninsula industry, taught at Bay de Noc Community College and continued to work on writing about Menominee and Cedar River history. He passed away in 1987.
During his career as editor both at the Herald-Leader and the Daily Press, Worth gained acclaim as an historian for those regions of the Upper Peninsula, especially in the areas of forestry and lumbering. He excerpted a great many notes from a half-dozen nineteenth and early twentieth century Menominee newspapers and developed a subject index for these materials as well.
The papers of Jean Worth consists largely of collected material relating to his research interest in Michigan's Upper Peninsula. The collection has been divided into the following series: Cedar River; Escanaba; Menominee; and Upper Peninsula -General.
Subjects:
Alcoholic beverage industry.; Breweries.; Cedar River (Mich.); Escanaba (Mich.); Grand Army of the Republic. Lyon Post, No. 266 (Menominee, Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan.; Logging--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Lumbering--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Menominee (Mich.); Menominee River Brewing Company.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Veterans--Michigan--Societies, etc.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Banks.; Boy Scouts of America.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Cedar River.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Menominee.; Carts and wagons.; Cedar River (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Cedar River (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Cedar River (Mich.)--Schools.; Cedar River (Mich.); City and town life.; Dwellings--Michigan--Cedar River.; Finnish Americans.; Fires--Michigan--Menominee.; Grand Army of the Republic. Lyon Post, No. 266 (Menominee, Mich.); Hotels and taverns.; Interiors.; Kitchens.; Lighthouses--Michigan.; Lumber industry.; Menominee (Mich.); Menominee (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Menominee (Mich.)--Fires.; Menominee (Mich.)--Schools.; Newspaper carriers.; Parades and processions.; Railroads--Michigan.; Schools--Michigan--Cedar River.; Schools--Michigan--Menominee.; Shipping--Great Lakes.; Stilts.; Tracklaying vehicles.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Wisconsin Land & Lumber Company.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Cedar River circa 1888-1982
  The Cedar River series, ca. 1888 to 1982, contains various papers used in presentations; photographs, mostly of area lumber operations as well as some corresponding negatives; and two unpublished manuscripts, one of which, "Cedar River," is a thirty-seven chapter history of the Cedar River area.
  - Papers and Presentations undated, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Photographs and Negatives
    - Negatives undated, circa 1906, 1914-1915, 40 negatives (in 2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Photographs
      - undated, 33 prints (in 2 folders) (Box 1)
      - 1888-1914, 8 photographs (Box 1)
      - 1889, 1894, 1900, circa 1906 (Box 1)
        (includes postcards)
      - circa 1914-1915, 1967 (Box 1)
      - Reprints, 6 prints (Box 1)
  - Unpublished Manuscripts
    - "Cedar River," 1982, 9 folders (Box 1)
      (arranged by chapter nos; two versions of chapter 5; missing chapter 8)
    - "Toots," undated (Box 1)
- Escanaba 1869-1986
  The Escanaba series, 1869 to 1986, is an alphabetically-arranged reference series. Topics covered include agriculture, airline service, the Bonifas Fine Art Center, Carnegie Library, economic conditions, railroads, St. Joseph's Parish, and sawmills. This series also contains notes taken from two early Escanaba newspapers, the Tribune from 1869 to 1876 and its successor, the Iron Post from 1877 to 1889.
  - Agriculture undated (Box 1)
  - Airline Service 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - Bonifas Fine Arts Center 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Library 75th Anniversary 1978 (Box 1)
  - Economic Conditions undated (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Excerpts
    - The Escanaba Tribune (Saturday weekly)
      - 1869-1876 (Box 1)
      - 1876-1877 succeeded by the Iron Post, 1877-1889 (Box 1)
  - Railroads undated (Box 1)
  - St. Joseph's Parish 1983 (Box 1)
  - Sawmills undated (Box 1)
- Menominee circa 1885-1985
  Menominee, ca. 1885 to 1985, contains two record books of the Menominee Grand Army of the Republic, Lyon Post 266; photographs and negatives; two minute books of the Menominee River Brewing Company; several manuscripts, of which one, "Menominee," is a forty-one chapter history of the Menominee area; and ten volumes of research notes.
  - Grand Army of the Republic-Lyon Post 266
    - Minute Book 1895-1929, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - Record Book, 1 volumes (Box 1)
      (compilation made in 1934)
  - Manuscripts
    - Published
      - Sketches of Menominee River, undated (Box 1)
        (typescript copy of 1871 original)
    - Unpublished
      - "Marinette and Menominee," undated (Box 1)
      - "Menominee," circa 1983-1985, 11 folders (Box 2)
        (arranged by chapters; also includes chronology and index)
      - "Menominee Indians," undated (Box 2)
      - "My Ten Year Old Experience," undated (Box 2)
      - "Personal Reminiscence of the Big Fire of 1871" undated (Box 2)
      - "Queen Marinette and John Jacob Astor," undated (Box 2)
  - Menominee River Brewing Company
    - Minute Books
      - 1891-1894, 1 volumes (Box 2)
      - 1894-1896, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Photographs and Negatives
    - Negatives: Street Scenes circa 1932, 12 negatives (Box 2)
    - Photographs
      - Fire Scenes undated, 1895, 1903, 1908, 8 prints (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous undated, circa 1900-1903, 22 prints (Box 2)
  - Research Notes (Box 3)
    - Volumes 1 and 2 (Box 3)
      (volumes consist mainly of interviews, reminiscences, and clippings)
    - Volume 3 (Box 4)
      (volume 3 consists mainly of interviews, reminiscences, and clippings)
    - Volume 4 (Box 4)
      (volume 4 contains excerpts taken from the Menominee Herald, 1885 to 1895, the Democrat, 1886 to 1897, the Daily Herald, 1894, and the Evening Leader (Menominee's first daily newspaper), 1893 and 1894)
    - Volume 5 (Box 5)
      (volume five contains the Democrat, 1895 to 1902, the Evening Leader, 1895 to 1902, the Daily Herald, 1895 to 1903, the Saturday Leader 1899 and 1902, and the Daily Leader, 1902)
    - Volume 6 (Box 5)
      (volume 6 contains the Daily Herald, 1903 and 1904, the Daily Leader, 1903 and 1904, and the Herald Leader, 1904 to 1917)
    - Volume 7 (Box 6)
      (volume 7 contains an unpublished manuscript, "Half Past Yesterday," which is arranged alphabetically by subject and written mostly from newspaper excerpts.)
    - Volume 8 (Box 6)
      (volume 8 is an alphabetically arranged subject index of Crier excerpts (A through L) during the 1940s.)
    - Volume 9 (Box 7)
      (volume 9 also contains an alphabetically arranged subject index of Crier excerpts from 1930s, 1940s and the early 1950s (M through Z) as well as some copied correspondence)
    - Index to volumes 1-9 (Box 7)
      (alphabetically-arranged subject index for the previous nine volumes, with citations to the volumes as well as to area newspapers he used)
- Upper Peninsula-General circa 1910-1986
  Upper Peninsula - General, ca. 1910 to 1986 is arranged alphabetically. It contains Worth's correspondence; his editorials on a number of subjects; and manuscripts, including a twenty-one chapter unpublished manuscript, "Back Door on Sunday," on the history of drinking in the Upper Peninsula.
  - Blaney Park undated (Box 8)
  - Cleveland Cliffs Iron Company
    - General undated (Box 8)
    - Health Services undated (Box 8)
  - Correspondence
    - Personal 1970-1986 (Box 8)
    - Professional 1951-1956, 1 volumes (Box 8)
  - Editorials
    - Bishop, George undated (Box 8)
    - French Names undated (Box 8)
    - Humor undated (Box 8)
    - Journalism undated (Box 8)
    - Medicine 1981 (Box 8)
    - Operation Action U.P. 1985 (Box 8)
    - Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe undated (Box 8)
    - Sesquicentennial circa 1986 (Box 8)
    - Taxes undated (Box 8)
    - Transportation 1978-1981 (Box 8)
    - Upper Peninsula State Fair circa 1986 (Box 8)
  - Energy 1983 (Box 8)
  - Forestry
    - Commercial Forest Act 1978-1983 (Box 8)
    - General 1969-1982 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Association of Timbermen-Address to 1982 (Box 8)
    - Northern Michigan Forest Fire Association; Northern Forest Protective Association 1910-1912 (Box 8)
    - Timber Producers Association of Michigan and Wisconsin-Presentations to 1986 (Box 8)
  - Indians undated (Box 8)
  - Manuscripts
    - Published
      - Hermansville (Chapter 5 excerpt from Jean Worth's book Alphabet Meyer's Machines) undated (Box 8)
    - Unpublished
      - "Back Door on Sunday" (History of Drinking in the Upper Peninsula) undated, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - "The Burying of Mary Finney," undated (Box 8)
      - "Cranberries of Whitefish Point," 1971 (Box 8)
      - "History of Upper Peninsula Breweries," 1957 (Box 8)
      - "We Built in Such a Logical Way," undated (Box 8)
  - Recreation undated (Box 8)
  - Vulcan, Michigan-History 1962 (Box 8)
  - Women 1972-1979 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Biographical (Box 8)
    - Photographs
      - Great Lakes Shipping 1930, 8 prints (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous undated, 1930, 7 prints (Box 8)